So originally, the
plan was to talk more
about reinforcement learning.
But I thought since I only
had one lecture to give,
I think this class
would be a little bit
incomplete without saying
something about multimodality,
which is so pervasive if you
look at all the major models.
So this will be an overview
of multimodal models.
Of course, this could be
a whole class in itself,
and I'll try to do what
I can in one lecture.
OK, so let's dive into
multimodal models.
So far in this class,
we have exclusively
focused on language models.
And language models are
already pretty general.
They give you the ability
to go from any piece of text
to any text.
So this could be any language,
code, poetry, anything you like,
even, let's say,
DNA, for example.
But the world is multi-modal.
You have text, you have
images, audio, video.
And if you think about a North
Star of where we want to be
is what people call
omni model, which
is ability to take any
combination of these modalities
and output any combination
of any of these modalities.
So, for example, I can give
you an image and a video
and I can ask a question
about the image and the video.
I can generate images.
I can convert the
audio into an image.
You can imagine all sorts
of different applications
by having an omni model.
So in this class, I'm
not going to build up
to a whole omni model.
But I'll give you some of the
pieces that at least to allow
you to ingest a little bit
of images, which we'll mostly
focus on today.
So how do you
build such a thing?
Well, this is a weird
way to motivate this,
but the reality is that
transformers work really well.
And despite the best efforts
of people to try other things,
those are across all of these
modalities still at scale
the best thing we have.
So we have to figure
out how to use them.
And now, transformers
were designed for text.
So they have this property
that they speak tokens.
So they take as input
a bunch of tokens
and then output some tokens.
And here, I'm
expanding the notion
of tokenization to be not just
a discrete token that we've
seen in text but also
potentially continuous tokens.
You can think about these
as embedding of tokens.
And the key thing
is that a token
should represent some
semantic unit of information.
For example, in natural
language, tokens are subwords.
And these are
somewhat meaningful.
Whereas, for example, a
pixel is certainly not
meaningful by itself.
So somehow we must
convert everything,
including audio and images, into
either discrete or continuous
tokens.
Now, notice that we've already
had to do this even with text.
In the first lecture, we
talked about tokenization.
And there, it was not too bad.
I mean, we had a BP tokenizer.
You guys implemented it.
It's fine.
One could wish for a better
tokenizer or something that
doesn't have tokenizers at all.
But it's not the worst
thing in the world.
Now, for non-text
modalities, we have
to scratch our heads a
lot more and figure out
what is the equivalent
of the BP tokenizer that
will take an image
and produce things
that a transformer can digest?
OK, so you have to answer
two questions here.
One is, for non-text data,
for example, images or videos
or audio, how do you input
these into the transformer?
And then how do you
generate them out?
And this lecture will mostly
focus on question number one.
OK, so let's start back and
rewind the clock back to 21.
So the CLIP model, which some
of you might be familiar with,
is a lot of the
foundation of modern VLMs.
And so we can go through
this a bit in more detail.
So CLIP stands for Contrastive
Language Image Pre-Training.
And a bit of historical
context is around
that time GPT-3 had
already happened.
GPT-2.
All the language
models had already
gone into this
foundation model era.
Neovision was still--
there were some efforts,
but traditionally had been
based on large annotated data
sets, such as ImageNet,
and training models,
such as the ResNet,
on these data sets
and doing a bunch of other
things, like data augmentation,
and getting really
good performance.
And so the researchers
at OpenAI were wondering,
is it possible to leverage
the large amount of image
and textual captions out there?
So inspired by this idea in
language where you could just
scrape the internet, you have
all this text, it's very noisy.
But somehow if you train
a large enough model,
you can make sense out of this
and generate something useful.
So what was the equivalent
of that for images?
So as a result, CLIP was born.
And the idea of CLIP is fairly
simple and straightforward.
So the idea here is
that suppose I give you
a bunch of image-text pairs.
So let's say I give
you 32,000 of these.
OK, so what I'm going
to do is for each image
I'm going to encode it using
an image encoder, which I'll
explain later, into a vector.
So I'm going to have 32,000
of these image encodings.
I'm going to also
do the same thing
with the corresponding text.
So that will give
me T1 through TN.
So these are the
embeddings of the text.
These are embedding
of the images.
Now, the objective
I want to set up
is that I want the
image-- let's take I1.
So I1 is aligned with T1.
So I want this alignment, the
dot product between these two
embeddings to be much larger
than the dot product between I1
and all the other texts, OK.
And conversely, I also
want for this text
to say that this dot
product is larger
than the dot product between
T1 and all the other images.
So that, in a nutshell,
is the CLIP objective.
And you can imagine
doing-- there's basically
2 times N different softmax
classification problems.
So here's the code.
So you get a n by d matrix
for the image encodings
and n by d times for
the textual embeddings.
You normalize and you
take this dot stop product
with some temperature.
And then you compute
the cross entropy, OK.
So it's basically a multi-class
classification problem,
where the examples are
structured in this m
by n matrix form.
OK, any questions about that?
All right, so some more details
about how CLIP was built.
So where does the
data come from?
There are not too many details
in the paper about the data.
Roughly, you take a bunch
of queries from somewhere
and then you go search
online for these
and you mine a bunch of
image and text pairs.
And this resulted in 400
million image-text pairs.
The data set wasn't
released, but there
was an effort by
this paper called
OpenCLIP, which replicated and
further extended the CLIP ideas.
So there was a data
set called LAION-5B,
which was released
5 billion images
with textual descriptions.
And there was a bunch of
processing that happened.
Interestingly, they actually
used CLIP for the data filtering
and then train OpenCLIP.
So there's some
bootstrapping happening.
But at least this
is a model where
you can point to the data
set that it was trained
on and the code as well.
So a few other details.
So images come in all
sorts of resolutions.
If you find an
internet image, it
might be long and
skinny or tall--
sorry.
Long and skinny
or the other way.
So arbitrary dimensions.
And one thing that you
learn about neural nets
is that they don't like
things to be dynamic.
They want things
to be fixed size.
So there is a somewhat
heuristic processing
that happens is they resize the
image so that the shorter side
is 336 or whatever target size.
It could be 224 as well.
And then they center
crop to get a square.
OK, this is obviously
for convenience.
Later, we'll see that you
can do better than this.
But this is just for expediency.
And also at this
time the CLIP authors
were thinking about
ImageNet and classification.
So usually, the object
is in the middle
and you're just trimming
off some background.
So it doesn't matter too much.
So what is the vision encoder?
So this is the
general algorithm.
But I haven't specified what
the image and text encoders are.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question I think is why
they train on image-text pairs
as opposed to images.
[INAUDIBLE]
So there is a line
of work that tries
to encode images
into representations
based on data augmentation.
So, for example, if you
take an image-- and I think
this idea called SimCLR.
You augment it.
You crop it.
You randomly perturb it.
Rotate it.
And you want to say that
that is the same image.
They should have
similar embeddings.
And that's useful for
low level details.
But the problem is
that you won't data
augment your way from one
type of dog to another dog.
So by using the
text, it gives you
a higher level semantic
representations of images.
And, yeah, that's
a good question.
And later, we'll see how these
semantic representations are
useful if you look
at the types of tasks
that people are trying to solve.
OK, so what is the vision
encoder that CLIP uses?
They actually experimented
with a bunch of different ones,
ResNets and vision transformers,
which had just come out.
They found out that vision
transformers performed the best.
So when people say CLIP, they
usually mean the VIT version.
And so a vision transformer
does the following.
So you take an image and you
break it up into these patches.
I think the original
paper was 16 by 16
and the CLIP used 14 by 14.
But anyway, you have
these little patches,
which are basically vectors.
So each patches
in some sense a--
well, a token for this
vision transformer.
You add the
positional embeddings
just like you would if you
were training a language model,
and then you just put it
through a standard transformer.
And if you want to
classify, then you would--
well, you would
usually want to--
OK, sorry.
The transformer encoder
produces a sequence of vectors.
And the CLIP paper does
something a little bit
different.
You can average
all these vectors.
That gives you a single vector.
But they thought it was better
to do attention pooling, which
means that you take the global
average of all the activations,
but then you also do
another round of attention
with that query against the key
and values of each position.
And that gives you
another vector,
which is maybe a little
bit more informed
rather than just a
straight up average.
OK, so that's the VIT.
And the CLIP paper found that
the best model is what is called
VIT-L/14.
So to decipher,
this is a large VIT.
I think it has 24 layers or so.
Not quite sure about that.
And 14 by 14 patches.
Each patch is RGB, so
it has three channels.
And they trained on 336
by 336 resolution images.
Actually, they
trained on a lower res
I guess for speed because high
resolution images take longer.
And then for the latter
part of training,
they train on higher res.
Yeah.
For the position
embedding, would it
be more complicated
than the task?
For example, task
only has [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, so the
question is, can you
be smarter about the
positional embeddings
because this is just
linear 0 through 9?
I think in this paper, they
actually-- in the CLIP paper,
I believe they tried
some 2D version of this.
And the one DNA found that it
doesn't really matter that much.
I think it's also--
I always have to take
these results with the idea
that they're interested
in classification in mind.
So for classification,
maybe it doesn't matter.
Later, we'll see a fancier
positional embeddings
that do take into account
the spatial structure.
OK, so the text encoder
is a standard transformer.
It's a GPT-2 style
transformer since that
was from the same group
that developed GPT-2.
And in order to get a single
vector out of a sequence,
they prepended BOS
and appended EOS.
And then they took EOS, the
activation at the highest layer
as the representation
of that whole sequence.
OK, so you have
the vision encoder.
You have the text encoder.
And then you can do
this process to train.
You pick a batch.
You encode all the text.
You decode all the images.
And then you form these two
end cross-entropy losses.
And then you go from there.
OK, so the headline
result, which
got a lot of people excited
about CLIP back in 2021,
is that on the
ImageNet benchmark,
0 shot CLIP outperform a
ResNet that was trained
on 1.2 million ImageNet images.
So if you think about
this, 1.2 ImageNet images,
this was many, many hours of
Amazon Mechanical Turk worker
time to do this annotation.
And now you have CLIP that was
trained on more organic web
data.
Of course, this was the labor
of a bunch of people on the web.
But if you're able to leverage
that or existing data already,
then you can just zero shot it.
And the zero shot
technique is basically
to explain I don't have
slide support here.
But you take an image and
then you have a bunch of text.
And then you basically
take the dot product
with the various labels and
see which one's the highest.
Oh, yeah.
It is.
Sorry.
It is on this part of the slide.
OK, good point.
So this is a zero
shot prediction,
where you take an image and
then you-- yeah, what I said.
Cool.
Any questions?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so the question
is if you have a dog
and there's maybe other
captions that also have dogs,
would that confuse the model?
In general, this process
is going to be noisy.
It's OK if there's another
dog because, on average, it's
unlikely that there's
always going to be a dog.
Sometimes it's going to be an
apple or a cat or something.
But also another point is that
these images are basically
scraped from images on the web
with textual text next to them
or in the alt image.
And so they're extremely noisy.
There's been studies
that look at when
you have a caption of an image,
it doesn't necessarily just
verbatim say what's
in the image.
Because if you have an
image and it's a dog,
you don't need to say a dog.
So this process is very noisy.
So it's maybe somewhat
surprising but also interesting
that it works.
I mean, there was a lot of
data filtering that is needed.
So if you take arbitrary
images on and text on that web,
it's probably going to
be too way too noisy.
One other thing to
note, which relates
to a point I'll come
back to at the very end,
is they also try this
alternative where
instead of doing this
ranking, they can
predict a text from the images.
So they can set
an objective where
they try to take the
images and predict
the text, either as a bag of
words or as a language model.
And they show that maybe,
I don't know, somewhat
surprisingly, that if
you use a stronger model,
it actually does
worse or at least
is less efficient compared
to using bag of words, CLIP.
So this is saying that--
I think saying that for
actually the representations
that you're trying to
learn-- or, again, this
is ImageNet accuracy.
So it's classification.
Actually modeling the exact
token sequences of the caption
isn't so important for getting
the rough representation
of the image.
OK, we'll come back to
this point at the end.
So what did we learned so far?
So we've encoded
images using CLIP.
And it captures the
semantics of the image
because it's paired with text.
And generally, text talks
about the semantics.
It is important to note that
the design decisions here are
based on image classification.
So it's not very fine-grained.
But yet, it's still,
as we'll see, serves
as a robust starting
point for everything
we're going to do later.
One technical downside of CLIP
is that it does require large
batch sizes, like 30,000.
If you have a batch
size of 1, clearly, it
doesn't work, or even
10, it doesn't work.
And furthermore, the
softmax operation
operates over the full batch.
So it's not really
very decomposable.
Whereas if you think about
normal language model
training, a batch of examples,
all the sequences parallelize
and you just do
aggregation at the end.
So this point will be addressed
by another paper from Google
that came out called SigLIP.
And so think about this as
basically an improved version
of CLIP.
So it stands for Sigmoid Loss
for Language Image Pre-training.
And here, the main
difference is that CLIP does
multi-class classification.
It says, I have this
aligned text and image.
And I'm going to say this
is positive against all
the other alternative
images or against all
the alternative text.
SigLIP, in some sense,
is a lot simpler.
It basically says for any
given image text pair,
are they aligned or not?
So if I reference
this diagram up here,
it's basically
binary classification
where the diagonals
are positive examples
and the diagonal are
negative examples.
That's it.
So here's the algorithm.
You take the embeddings.
You normalize.
You take the dot
product as usual.
But now you're forming the
labels which are minus 1
on the off-diagonal, and
diagonals you have one.
And then you do log_sigmoid.
So the objective is very simple.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so the question
is, does this
require any sophisticated
sampling strategies?
At least in the
initial paper, they
were just operating on literally
the same type of matrix.
You could imagine I think you're
probably thinking in general
for these contrastive methods.
The negative examples
need to be-- sometimes
you need to balance the
positives and the negatives,
or the negatives need to
be like tight negatives
so that you're not biased.
But at least in the
initial version,
this was fairly straightforward.
So to speak about the data,
this was done at Google.
This was the data set.
They used another paper, which
was another language image
model around 2022, which got
a WebLI data set with order
billion image text pairs.
They also did some extra work.
For example, images
that have text in them.
They did OCR.
And that's another way
to form text image pairs
and did some filtering.
This was multilingual.
The main point of this paper
was that it was much more
efficient to train than CLIP.
So CLIP was trained
10 days on 256 TPUv3,
and CLIP was five days on 32v4s.
And you might think,
oh, v4s actually
should be faster than v3.
In terms of flops per
second, they're actually not.
They're better because you
can put more of them in a pod
and the interconnect is better.
But at this scale, it's
really actually not faster.
Actually, 60%
slower or something.
So the way that this is
faster-- and, of course,
I think CLIP
probably did not try
to optimize the code for
the maximum throughput.
It was just let's get
this thing to work.
But the SigLIP paper showed
that you can parallelize this
as follows.
So you have-- basically, if you
recall your systems lecture,
so this is you can think
about it as DDP if you like,
where each device stores a
subset of the image text pairs.
However, there's interactions
between the examples,
unlike in language model
training, where everything just
factors.
So in the first
pass, each device
just computes all the losses
on whatever image text
pairs it has locally.
And then you send the text.
So basically, device
1 gets T5 through T8.
And now it's able to
compute the negatives here.
And then it gets T9 through T12.
So you rotate around until you
cover all the off-diagonal block
entries.
Another thing that
was nice about SigLIP
is that you effectively
decoupling batch size
from the loss.
Whereas in CLIP, the loss
is tied to the batch size.
If you change the batch size,
it's a different loss function.
So they were able to experiment
with much smaller batch sizes
less than 16K.
And in that regime, it's
much better than CLIP
because the loss
function, if you
have too many too small a
batch size, it just degrades.
Whereas for smaller batch size
for CLIP, you have more variance
but it's the same
in expectation.
It's the same loss.
They also say, well, you can go
up to much larger batch sizes.
But that doesn't really help.
And we saw that critical
batch sizes at some limit.
And 32K was essentially
their critical batch size.
OK, so now we have
CLIP and SigLIP.
These are image encoders that
take an image, in this version,
just a fixed size image, 336
by 336, let's say, and maps it
into a vector, OK, which
contains some semantics.
So now let's start building
VLMs, Vision Language Models.
And I'm going to talk about
two families of models, LLaVA
and Qwen.
The two are very similar
in the broad template.
There are some details
that are different,
which we'll go through,
and the basic idea
is that we're going to
take these embeddings
and then just inject them
into our language model.
So this is going to be more
of a flavor of mid-training
or post-training, where we
take an existing image encoder.
We take an existing
LLM, and then we're
going to stitch it together
rather than training something
from scratch.
So LLaVA paper came out in 2023.
And this got people excited
because around this time,
the closed models, like
GPT, I think it was GPT-4,
was able to do visual reasoning.
And they were able to
show that they could do
some visual reasoning as well.
It wasn't as good
as GPT-4, of course,
but I think it was an
open model and people
got to see what
went under the hood.
So for VLMs, there's
essentially a few pieces here.
There's the vision encoder.
They use CLIP here.
For the text decoder, they use
a language model called Vicuna,
which is the first Llama
model that was fine-tuned
on some shared
GPT conversations.
So these are conversations
that people have with ChatGPT
and share them on this website.
I don't think this
is up anymore.
So the data that they
used was based on MS COCO.
So this was an
annotated data set
where they had Mechanical
Turk workers go and annotate
a bunch of images with bounding
boxes and captions describing
what was in the image.
So they basically synthesized
a data set for their model.
So they prompted GPT-4 with the
captions or the detected objects
and GPT-4 to generate
questions or conversations.
For example, this is an image
in the MS COCO data set.
This was an annotated
caption done by a human.
And also here is also
annotated by a human.
And then you ask GPT-4,
generate me a conversation
and you might get a
question and an answer.
You might ask GPT-4 generate
me a detailed description.
It generates something, I
guess, similar to the caption.
And then you can ask GPT-4 to
generate complex reasoning.
And it does something like that.
OK, so those are synthesized
data, 158,000 examples.
And then they trained
a model on this.
So the model-- so they
use CLIP, in particular,
the highest performing
CLIP version, VITL/14.
So 14 by 14 patches.
And then they-- let's
just look at this image.
So they take images.
They send it through
this vision encoder CLIP.
That gives you a vector.
But this vector isn't
really in the same space,
so to speak, as the text.
So then they multiply
by a matrix W
to get another vector, which is
in the same space as the text
embeddings.
And for text, you basically just
use your standard embeddings
to get vectors.
So what's basically happening
is that the text gets encoded
into these vectors and
the image also gets
encoded into these vectors.
And then this whole
sequence of vectors
just goes through a standard
transformer and produces output.
OK, so we're in some sense
converting these images
into textual tokens.
So I can leverage the
pre-trained language model.
So to train this model,
they do it in two stages.
The first stage is that
they freeze the vision
encoder and the language model
and only train this matrix W.
And this is what they call
the alignment phase, which
is essentially making
sure that the image gets
mapped into the same space.
Because if you just
use a random W,
these images are
not going to be--
I mean, certainly,
they're not embeddings,
representing any
natural language token.
So the goal of
training W is that they
look like natural
language token embeddings.
And the second stage
is that they now
still freeze a vision
encoder and then train
W and the language model.
So they're fine-tuning the
language model on their data.
So remember, their data is
basically here's an image
and here is a conversation
or a description
or a complex reasoning example.
So this is all image
plus text to text.
OK, so this is one
example from their paper.
It's interesting.
So you have an input
image and a conversation.
The user says what's
unusual about this image.
And their model is able to
tell you that you don't usually
iron on the back of a minivan.
And they also make a point
that their model is pretty good
because even if your
user prompt is not really
prompting the unusualness, it
still talks about it, whereas--
GPT-4, obviously,
is able to do this,
but other models at the
time were not able to.
OK, any questions about LLaVA?
OK, so that was 2023.
And I'm going to skip forward to
LLaVA OneVision, which is 2024.
There is a sequence of papers
after the LLaVA paper came out
of LLaVA 1.5, LLaVA-Next.
But I'll capture all of
these innovations, I think,
in what I'll describe next.
The main thing that they
did is it's essentially
the same recipe,
but they are trying
to be more ambitious
in terms of the types
of multimodal applications
they could do.
So they were able to handle
multiple images and videos.
So here's the same diagram.
Now they can take a single
image or multiple images
or a video, which is
essentially a sequence of images
corresponding to a
sampling of the frames.
And here are the vision encoder.
They upgrade it to SigLIP.
The text decoder,
they use Qwen-2 now,
which was probably the
best language model
that was out at that time.
And then for the projector
or the adapter, which
is the thing that takes the
output of the vision encoder
and turns it into the
input of the language model
is a two-layer MLP instead
of a linear projection.
OK, so it's like
you have a system
and you're just
upgrading the parts.
But it's the same rough system.
So let's talk a little
bit about data processing.
So one thing that they
wanted to do is to do OCR.
And the thing with
OCR is that you
need to preserve very
fine-grained information.
Otherwise, a J looks like
an I, and that's not good.
So remember that CLIP resizes
and crops to 336 by 336.
And clearly, if
you have a document
and you crop to 336 by
336, you can't read it.
So their solution
is this idea called
AnyRes, which was actually
introduced in the LLaVA 1.5
paper.
And the idea is
basically, I mean,
it's fairly straightforward.
You break up an image
into multiple pieces.
And the idea is that each piece
is the resolution of whatever
the vision encoder is going to
take, 336 by 336, for example.
So you're going to code all the
pieces into a bunch of vectors.
And then you
concatenate the vectors.
OK, so you're basically noticing
that your vision encoder
can't handle high resolution.
So rather than
downsampling, you're
just going to crop and look
at different parts of image.
And now if you have really super
high resolution images or videos
then, you get too many tokens.
So then they downsample.
But the idea behind AnyRes
is that it's adaptive.
And this is nice because the
transformer is already adaptive.
Language can be-- your
sentences can be any length
and the transformer already
handles that pretty well.
So it turns out images
can be any resolution.
So that's picking back on
the same dynamic ability.
So here is what they
actually do for images here.
So let's say you have
this image of a paper.
They do downsample
and have one path,
which is basically a downsampled
encoding of the entire paper.
But then they break it
up into these chunks,
where each chunk
is the resolution
that the vision encoder expects,
and then encodes each of these
separately.
And then you concatenate
all these patches.
And if you have
too many, then you
reduce that the number of
patches by interpolation.
OK, so then they're able to
handle images, multiple images,
and video.
So you think about,
well, all of these
are technically all
reducible to images,
but they put their thumb
on the scale a little bit
because they want to make sure
all the modalities are roughly
comparable.
Because videos can
be very long, they
don't want their data
set to be dominated
by a bunch of repetitive frames.
So here's what they do here.
So for a single
image, they basically
have the full image
downsampled and then
a bunch of crops up to
N crops there, up to 9.
And if you are presented
with multiple images,
then they just use
the base resolution.
So if you have a
single image, I get
to look at it more carefully.
If I have multiple
images, I'm just
going to look at it from afar.
And for video, we're going
to use even lower resolution
or fewer tokens to represent
each frame because the idea is
that, well, videos can be--
they only use up to 32 frames,
but you start running
into context length
problems for viewing.
And later, we'll
see how a big part
of being able to
handle multimodal
is to deal with longer context.
OK, so the data here that
they use is, I would say,
the state of philosophy is they
want to curate high quality data
and quantity.
Another way to interpret this
is that it's very targeted data.
If you look at many of
these, it's very task-based
whether you're doing visual
question answering or answering
questions about tables.
So this is definitely
post-training territory,
where you're trying to get
your model to do these tasks,
and therefore, you create
a bunch of these tasks.
And this work is also
unabashedly, basically,
distilling GPT-4
models so that they
can get the best performance,
which is, I guess, not ideal.
But this is what you do if you
don't have an annotation budget.
And so they have single images,
multiple images, and videos.
So there's a lot of
different pieces.
Some of these are very specific.
You give two images and you're
trying to spot the difference.
But one thing that--
OK, I'll come back to
this at this point later.
So for training, it's roughly
the same idea as before,
where the first stage is that
you're focused on alignment.
So in particular, you
only train the projector,
which is the adapter.
And then in the second
stage and the third stages
you train the full model.
And before, we had two stages.
Now, we have three stages.
I'm not sure there's any
particular principled reason
for this, except for
this second stage is
trying to put high quality data
but more focused on knowledge.
And the final stage is
focusing on examples that look
like your downstream tasks.
OK, so one thing that they
found in this paper, which
was interesting, is that you
get transfer between modalities.
So even though they have
only single image data
for diagrams and charts,
but this actually
generalizes to multiple images.
So at training time,
you never saw an example
where you have a
table and a chart
and you're asking
questions about it.
But at test time, you have
two images, one for the table
and one for the chart.
And you're able to have some
of conversation about it.
At training time, you only have
OCR data on single image data,
and you only have relational
reasoning from multiple images.
But you can generalize
to these cases which
are useful for
powering GUI agents,
where you show it a
bunch of screenshots.
This is multiple images and
it can generate a description
of the screenshots.
Another example
is that they have
this idea of visual
prompting, where
you have this circle, which
is a part of the image,
but that's meant to highlight
the part of the image
that you're supposed
to do something about.
And this type of data only
exists for single images.
And now it can
generalize to videos
where the user says describe the
player highlighted in the video.
And this player is
across multiple frames.
So when you first look
at this and say, oh, boy.
You're basically targeting
each of these tasks.
It's supervised learning.
But if you have enough
tasks, these models
seem to do some transfer,
which is, I guess, reassuring.
OK, so again, this is
a fairly standard VLM
template, vision encoder plus
the projector into the language
model.
There's a lot of work that
goes into the data curation.
They lean pretty heavily into
synthesize task-specific data.
The nice thing about
the LLaVA series
is that it's one of the few
works that open sources.
They're not just the model
weights, but also the data.
So you can really replicate
and study this stuff.
OK, now let's talk
about the Qwen Models.
So Qwen started also training
in 2023 multimodal models.
So the first
version was Qwen-VL.
And hopefully, I'll
go through this
quickly because you
hopefully see the pattern.
The vision encoder,
they use Open-CLIP.
Remember, OpenCLIP was the open
reproductions of the CLIP model.
So it's basically
a CLIP encoder.
And for the adapter, they did
one layer of cross-attention,
incorporate 2D positional
embeddings and maps to a fixed
size of 256, which
is a little bit--
I guess this will be changed
later because this is definitely
not very dynamic, but
neither is the vision encoder
at this point.
I guess this got cut off.
But the special
tokens, they have
an image tag and a box
tag for bounding box,
and a ref tag for descriptions.
This is what happens when
your slides are in HTML.
So for training, they
have three stages, just
like with the LLaVA models.
In the first stage,
the idea is to--
I mean, they call it
pre-training but you're not
pre-training from scratch.
This is generally
large-scale, low quality data.
They freeze the
language model and train
the vision encoder and adapter.
So this is a bit different
from the LLaVA models, in
that, they train the vision
encoder at this point.
And you can see some of the data
sets that they are training on,
1.4 billion examples.
Stage 2, they move to higher
quality task-specific data.
And you can see some of the
usual suspects of VQA data sets,
chart question
answering, and so on.
And then they train all
the parameters here.
And finally, stage 3 is
instruction tuning data.
You freeze the visual encoder
and you train the adapter
and the language model.
Here are some examples
of the type of things
that they're able to do.
So, of course, this is Qwen.
So some of these
examples are in Chinese.
Their interest is
also making a model
that is supposed to be
subsuming a language model.
So a language model can do code.
So we want the vision model
to be good at code as well.
And you can have this example,
if you can see it, is an image.
And can you find
Spider-Man and the Hulk.
And it can output
bounding boxes as well.
It doesn't actually
output an image.
It just outputs a bounding box.
And then you can do OCR.
You can compare--
so usual stuff.
OK, so then Qwen-2
was, again, a upgrade.
There's some new ideas
here, which I'll go through.
So use a larger vision encoder.
They also started doing
dynamic resolution.
I think this was the main thing.
We remember when we went from
LLaVA to LLaVA OneVision,
they realized, oh,
we need to handle
images of different sizes.
And if you try to
do video, it's clear
that you need some
dynamic resolution.
So the model is basically-- so
let's say you have this picture
here, that might be
mapped to 11,000 tokens.
This tiny picture of an equation
might be only mapped to 8 tokens
and so on and so forth.
So how do they do this?
Well, basically each-- it's
the same idea AnyRes idea
from LLaVA, where each 224 by
224 patch is encoded with a VIT.
And remember the VIT
that they started
with is the OpenCLIP bit.
But this gets fine-tuned.
And then trying to
reduce the contact size,
they compress
every 2 by 2 into 1
so that they ultimately edge
every patch generates 66 tokens.
For eight videos, they sample
2 frames a second but max out
at 16,000 tokens.
OK, so one thing coming
back to this question
about positional
embeddings, so they did
do something different
here with Qwen-2.
So they used this idea called
multimodal rotary, multimodal
RoPE.
So remember, we saw RoPE before.
And the idea behind RoPE is
that you have embedding such
that the inner product
between the vectors
depends only on the distance.
So the distance is defined in
1D by just the number of tokens.
You're away from it.
So now, the
multidimensional version
is essentially the same thing.
Except for now you have 3D.
So you have height.
You have width
and you have time.
So each position, each
patch now is a triple
defined by the coordinates.
And then to compute the M-RoPE,
basically, for every dimension,
you compute the RoPE and
then you concatenate.
So it's a fairly
straightforward idea.
Although, later,
with Qwen-3, we'll
see how this is actually
a bit suboptimal.
So they initialize the
language model with--
this is the Qwen-VL model.
So, of course, they're
initializing with Gwen.
And then they have three
stages of training,
which is very similar
to what we did before.
And then they were
able to show a bunch
of different capabilities,
some video understanding.
It can do math and
code, function calling,
and so on and so forth.
OK, so quickly, I'll
talk about Gwen-3.
So again, there's
a few changes here.
I wouldn't say these are
structural big changes,
but they're probably
changes that do impact
the quality of the model.
So this is from last
year Gwen3-VL report.
And so it's roughly
the same diagram here.
I'll point out maybe--
I'll come back to this diagram.
I'll go through
some of the changes.
So one is that now they're
using Qwen-3 models.
They have a series of
dense and MoE models.
And the Qwen-3 models
are really, really good,
and it really helps the
quality of the final model.
One thing that they're vested in
is long context understanding.
So their context length
can go up to 256K,
which is really important if
you're trying to do long video.
Let's talk about
the vision encoder.
So they use SigLIP-2,
which is basically
an improved version of SigLIP.
It's actually
identical architecture,
is designed to be
backward compatible.
And then they
improved their RoPE.
And the way to explain
this is, before, you
had the three dimensions,
time, width, and height.
And basically, when
to basically allocate
the first block of
dimensions to the time,
then the next block to width
and the next to height.
And the problem, if
you remember RoPE
is that each component
refers represents
a different frequency.
So this would mean that maybe
all the temporal dimensions
are low frequency and
all the high dimensions
are high frequency.
So they basically interleave
them when they realize that.
And they now all
the axes are exposed
to both low and high frequency.
Another thing they did was
explicit video timestamps.
So if you look closely at this--
wait.
OK, this is Qwen-3.
Oops.
So if you look--
this is probably a
little bit too small.
But before, the time
stamp was implicit
in the positional encodings.
Each frame in the
video intrinsically
gets a different--
there's a notion of time
just because it's in
a different position.
But here, they made
the time explicit.
So these are actually
tokens zero seconds,
is a token that is now
you have a token that
represents the time.
And they found this to be
helpful presumably because it's
something that you
can directly refer to,
like what happened
after two seconds.
So that is one of
the main changes.
They also did this square root
normalized per token loss.
So the idea is that
some examples that
involve video are very long
and some examples that involve
a single image are very short.
And the normal thing is that
every token is treated the same.
And this would mean
that the video examples
are going to dominate.
So they basically-- the
details aren't too clear.
But I believe they
normalized each example
by the square root of the
length to basically downweight
the impact of really
long examples.
The final thing that is worth
noting, which is interesting,
is that they did something
interesting with adapter.
So remember we
started the adapter is
the thing that connects the
vision encoder to the language
model.
And LLaVA was the simplest.
It was just a linear projection.
And then we got an MLP.
And then we got some
cross-attention.
And DeepStack, which is actually
a paper from the DeepSeek team,
but when used here is
more sophisticated.
They noticed that, well, the
vision encoder already computes
a stack of vision embeddings.
And we're basically
going to basically add
these directly into the residual
stream of the language model.
OK, so this is a bit more of
a deep fusion of the vision
encoder into the language model
as opposed to the vision encoder
is a black box that just
outputs a sequence of vectors.
OK, so training is--
so they have two phases.
Pre-training has
actually four stages.
Post-training has three stages.
So you can see that
this pipelines are
getting quite complicated now.
So they first train the adapter.
This is the same as
all of these models.
And then they have three stages
where they progressively train
on longer and longer sequences,
from 8K, to 32K, to 256K.
Most of the tokens are
in the stages 2 and 3.
And then for
post-training, they do
SFT on long chain of thought
data, knowledge distillation,
and then some
reinforcement learning.
At this point, it's
really a systems paper.
There's a bunch of--
I highlighted the
core new ideas,
but there's a lot of
details that are different.
And if you look at
the final results,
this is a pretty good model.
I mean, if you look at
these benchmarks as compared
to the closed models
Gemini, GPT-5, and Opus 4.1,
these numbers are--
the bold means that it's
the best number in that row.
So the Qwen models are
actually quite strong.
OK, maybe the--
yeah, a question.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so the question is
what about video generation
and how do you know whether
there should be a video or text?
So first of all, these models
don't generate videos or images.
All the multimodal stuff
is on the input side.
You're always generating text.
And then you're always in most
of these stages, except for RL,
you're supervising every token.
So there's no LLM as a
judge or quality on how well
the description is working.
It's just basically whatever
is in your data set.
Now, with RL, you can play
around with different rewards.
Yeah.
I'll ask is the training
of multimodal models
harder than training a pure
LLM from a system perspective?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so the two questions are
trained multimodal models harder
on the system side?
And, I mean, certainly,
it's not easier.
I think you pointed out that
the data sets are larger.
Video data is just-- even
loading it can be a bottleneck.
Whereas generally,
we have not really
focused on data loading for
talking about language models
because it's very, very cheap.
So that needs to be
taken into account.
And all the same
principles of making sure
that your data
loading is happening
async with actual computation
needs to be taken into account.
And the second part was--
sorry, what was the
second question?
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, yeah.
So the videos and images
can have more-- especially
video have more tokens.
So that's one reason we
saw this normalization
to make sure that we're not
giving more weight to video.
I mean, you can
always down weight.
So if you have more tokens,
if you don't like that,
you can down weight.
We talked in the last or two
weeks ago about data mixtures.
So you can always
weight things according
to whatever makes sense.
But there's also a lot
of text tokens out there.
So I think, in general,
if you look at, yeah,
the models are trained on
tens of trillions of tokens.
I think there's a--
yeah, I wouldn't
say that the number
of multimodal tokens
vastly outnumbers text tokens.
Yeah, oh, I think
you were first.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, when
you do this alignment,
how does it know what the
language-- is the model language
model pre-trained?
And it definitely has to be
pre-trained because otherwise it
doesn't make sense to align it.
So the language model is frozen.
And you're just
training the adapter
to connect the given vision
encoder with a given language
model.
And the way you
train it is, well,
you pick a token budget,
67 billion tokens
and you just train.
There's not an adaptive
threshold here.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so the question
is, is the number
of parameters in the
vision coder much smaller?
And the answer is
yes, in general.
I'm trying to find--
where is the other place I--
not here.
OK, the reason is that
the vision encoder
is in some sense doing
a very local operation.
It's looking at a patch.
A patch is very small.
And it's just trying to
understand the patches.
There's not much knowledge.
So the patch, we're
not reasoning.
So most of the
capabilities of the model
are still in the language model.
I'm trying to find the--
OK, where?
Maybe it was up here.
OK, I can't-- oh, yeah.
So if you look at the
LLaVA model, so the full--
so 72 billion parameter
language model.
Sorry.
What-- OK, I don't know why
this number is so-- oh, sorry.
This is 72 million, OK.
So this is much smaller.
The projector is much smaller.
And the VIT is generally less
than a billion, parameters.
Yeah, I guess mostly because
it's fairly a local operation.
I guess that's the
easy way to say it.
OK, I'm going to think
some other questions.
I'm going to try to move on now.
So I Qwen-3 is the last
vision language model.
I'll talk about this SOTA,
Save Our Performance.
There's a lot of data
work that happens.
Not too many details
about the data
and the data mix in
these later Qwen models.
So you'll have to look at
the LLaVA paper or the--
AI2 has a [INAUDIBLE]
paper, which
I didn't get a chance
to talk about that
has more details here.
And from Qwen to Qwen-2, Qwen-3,
many of these changes were
mostly--
there's some changes there.
But the overall framework
remains the same.
And mostly, it's scaling
up, curating more data sets,
noticing that your context
isn't-- you have to handle long
context and maybe sharpening
your image processing and so on.
OK, so I'm going to now jump
to something quite different.
So there's this paper called
Chameleon from Meta in 2024.
So, so far, VLMs encode
images into these vectors
and then they inject them
into a language model.
And because it's
a language model,
you can only generate text.
You can't generate images.
So there's many ways you
can go about fixing this.
You can just take a VLM.
You can also attach
a diffusion head.
And now you can
generate images or--
but I want to talk
about this idea here,
which is Chameleon says,
what if we mapped everything
into discrete tokens?
And in some ways
aesthetically this is--
well, maybe this reflects
that I'm a language person.
This is appealing because now
you can analyze and generate
images in the same way.
Everything is a discrete token.
If you want to do what--
let's say you want
to generate images.
You can say, here's
a text prompt.
And then you can just--
these are more just
tokens that you can generate.
Or you can flip the language
and the text around as well.
They have these examples
from the Chameleon paper
you can prompt in say I'm bored.
Can you show me some birds?
And then it would
be text, and then it
would be images, and then some
more text and some images.
So it's interleaved.
So in some sense, the
vision of an omni model
is that text and images
truly live in the same space.
And this is accomplished
by making everything look
like text.
That's one way to do it.
OK, so I'll talk a little
bit about how this is done.
So the thing you need to
do now is to map images
into discrete tokens.
So there's this idea
rather old from Oord 2017,
which is called vector quantized
variational autoencoder.
And the basic idea
here is to map an image
into a discrete code.
And what you learn is a
mapping that maps this
into a continuous vector.
And this gets rounded
to the nearest code.
So you have a codebook which
has, let's say, 8,000 codes.
So these are prototypical
vectors that correspond to what
patches.
And then so you pick one of
these that's the closest.
And that would be
your representation.
So that's your encoder.
It goes through a
continuous phase
and then you round it
to the nearest code.
And now the decoder
is you take that code
and you try to
reconstruct the image.
And then you train these
VQ-VAEs by basically minimizing
the reconstruction loss.
There are some
other terms that you
add because this is not
differentiable, which
I won't have time to get into.
OK, but, at the end of the day,
you have 512 by 512 images that
are converted into 1,024 tokens,
and each token comes from
a vocabulary of 8,000.
OK, so now you have
basically text.
You have your images, which
are basically these codes.
They train a new
tokenizer because now you
have different-- your data
looks different than if it were
just normal natural language.
The training is now actually
very straightforward.
This is just normal
language model training.
There's no adapter.
There's no turn
the vision encoder.
There's just a
language model now.
So this is the part
that's appealing.
So there's still two stages.
But even for language
model training,
there's usually
two or more stages,
where the first stage
is the bulk of training.
It's largely unsupervised.
They have both text
and text and image.
And then stage 2, they
mix in high quality data.
OK, so this is really
great and elegant.
There's a few
problems with this.
One is that they found that
the training was not stable.
And the reason is
that text and images,
despite occupying
the same space,
just behave very differently.
So just calling
things discrete tokens
isn't hiding the fact that
there's an image living there.
And in particular,
text tokens, if you
think about predicting
the next word,
this has relatively
lower entropy.
Most words are predictable,
whereas image tokens
have very high entropy.
I don't know what shade of blue
this exact token is going to be.
And so as a result, they found
that training with this mixture
led to a lot of the
norms of the parameters
to grow and to generate
loss instability.
They were able to
mitigate or fix this
to some extent via QK norm and
z-loss regularization, which
controls the norm growth.
So I'm not even going
to show the results.
But I wanted to highlight
this work because there's
a certain elegance here because
it's just one model that treats
really all modalities the same.
But the downside is
that it turned out
this model was not
really as performant,
and the discretization does
definitely lose its information.
So think about OCR.
Again, if you discretize
very small print,
you're not going to be
able to read it anymore.
And finally, training with
multi modalities is also tricky.
We saw this a little
bit with the Qwen models
and we had to play
around with the weights.
But this is more
exacerbated here.
So VQ-VAEs were
popular for a while.
And in fact, many people were
using this for image generation.
The main reason to do that is,
well, you have a transformer.
How do you generate
from a transformer?
Well, you have to
generate discrete things
and you basically put all your
data into this discrete form.
But then diffusion
models came out
and became popular and
viable for generation.
So this flavor of method is
less popular than it used to be.
OK, so maybe just reflect
and summarize here.
Frontier models these
days are expected
to be multimodal or even more
strongly natively multimodal
or omni models.
Unfortunately, I think
when Gemini comes out
or GPT comes out,
they tout or touted
as being natively multimodal
and handle all these modalities.
And in fact, they do.
But of course,
there's no details
about how these are built.
I think that it's
probably combination
of having a continuous
encoder because you don't want
to lose information and then
diffusion for the generation
because-- but that's
my speculation.
The fundamental
challenge, I think,
when you're dealing
with multimodality
is how do you handle
non-text modalities?
It's also interesting
that there's
a asymmetry between
understanding the modality
and generation.
And there's no one
universal encoder let's say.
For example, when
we looked at CLIP,
you only cared
for classification
to capture high level semantics.
So these vectors
could be fairly small
and capture the high
level semantics.
Whereas if you wanted to do
OCR or whether you wanted
to generate an image, then you
need really fine-grained detail.
You need to-- that's why
diffusion is so good because it
can really micro optimize the
low-high frequency information.
I think, in general,
when you're dealing
with multiple modalities,
you have to think carefully
about weighing them properly.
For example, video certainly
has lower information density
than text.
So you don't want a video
to overwhelm your text.
And like I said before, at
least the current best thing
is having continuous encoders.
It seems even CLIP, even
though it's five years old,
or similar ideas are
still the go-to way
to capture semantics of images.
Transformers are still there.
And then diffusion models,
which I didn't talk about,
are great for generation.
OK, so I will stop there.
That's it for the
lecture on multimodality.
I guess we don't have any
homework on doing this.
But if you're curious,
I think I encourage
you to play around with
training some of these models.